Koyl-Mathieson Collection
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Koyl-Mathieson Collection 1963-1969
MSS86351
Koyl, George S. (George Simpson), 1885-1975
Mathieson, Moira B.
8,500 items
24 containers
9.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Architectural drawings, surveys, correspondence, subject files, and related research material used to compile an architectural catalog.
Acquisition Information
The Koyl-Mathieson Collection was transferred from the Library of Congress Prints and Photographs Division in 2019.
Access and Restrictions
The Koyl-Mathieson Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Biographical Note for George S. Koyl and Moira B. Mathieson
George S. Koyl was born February 8, 1885, in Evanston, Wyoming. He studied architecture at the University of Pennsylvania and the American Academy in Rome. He worked as an architect in Colorado and New York, and later opened up his own independent firm. He then partnered with the firm Rich, Mathesius & Koyl in 1929. He left the firm in 1932 to work as the Dean of the School of Fine Arts at the University of Pennsylvania. He retired in 1950 and worked as a professor of architecture until 1955. Koyl was the president of the American Institute of Architects (AIA) chapter in Pennsylvania from 1943 to 1944 and served on its executive committee from 1943 to 1946.
Moira B. Mathieson was born around 1924. She became a freelance writer and editor after a career in architecture and art history. From 1963 to 1969, she was the Head of Architectural Drawings Project, Department of Civil History at the Smithsonian Institution. Together, Koyl and Mathieson compiled and edited American Architectural Drawings: a Catalog of Original and Measured Drawings of Buildings of the United States of America to December 31, 1917 (1969), which was funded by a Kress Foundation grant and prepared and published through the Philadelphia Chapter of the AIA.
Scope and Content Note
The Koyl-Mathieson Collection spans the years 1963-1969 and consists of research material for American Architectural Drawings: a Catalog of Original and Measured Drawings of Buildings of the United States of America to December 31, 1917 (1969), compiled and edited by George S. Koyl and Moira B. Mathieson and prepared and published through the Philadelphia Chapter of the American Institute of Architects, and for Addendum to American Architectural Drawings (1977) by James M. Goode.
The States and Countries File contains architectural drawings, pamphlets, newspaper clippings, and surveys related to buildings and other structures, most of which date from the eighteenth century to the early twentieth century. The Correspondence series primarily documents the publishing of the architectural catalog, and includes correspondence with museums, architectural archives and associations, the Kress Foundation and other organizations, and suppliers. The Subject File includes architectural surveys, printed matter, manuals, and reports. The Architects series has biographical material and other appropriate information on various architects compiled for the catalog.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in four series:
States and Countries File, 1963-1969
Correspondence, 1963-1969
Subject File, 1963-1969
Architects, 1963-1969
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Goode, James M. Addendum to American architectural drawings: compiled February 1977 ... from unpublished surveys of the location of American architectural drawing prepared by the AIA, Phila. Chapter, but not included in the 5 vol. publication compiled and edited by George S. Koyl, 1969.; Koyl, George S. (George Simpson), 1885-1975, American architectural drawings; a catalog of original and measured drawings of buildings of the United States of America to December 31, 1917.; Koyl, George S. (George Simpson), 1885-1975.; Mathieson, Moira B.; Mathieson, Moira B., American architectural drawings; a catalog of original and measured drawings of buildings of the United States of America to December 31, 1917.
Organizations
American Institute of Architects. Philadelphia Chapter.
Subjects
Architects--United States.; Architectural drawing.; Architecture--United States.
Titles
Koyl-Mathieson index to architectural records
Occupations
Architects.; Editors.; Educators.
Container List
- State and Countries File, 1963-1969 (Box 1-15)
  Architectural drawings, pamphlets, newspaper clippings, and surveys related to buildings and other structures.
  Arranged alphabetically by location.
  - Alabama-California, 1963-1969, (102 folders) (Box 1)
  - California-Delaware, 1963-1969, (79 folders) (Box 2)
  - Delaware-District of Columbia, 1963-1969, (47 folders) (Box 3)
  - District of Columbia-Georgia, 1963-1969, (84 folders) (Box 4)
  - Georgia-Kentucky, 1963-1969, (83 folders) (Box 5)
  - Louisiana, 1963-1969, (63 folders) (Box 6)
  - Louisiana-Maryland, 1963-1969, (37 folders) (Box 7)
  - Massachusetts-New Hampshire, 1963-1969, (63 folders) (Box 8)
  - New Jersey-New York, 1963-1969, (105 folders) (Box 9)
  - New York-Oklahoma, 1965-1967, (67 folders) (Box 10)
  - Oregon-Pennsylvania, 1963-1969, (67 folders) (Box 11)
  - Pennsylvania-Virginia, 1963-1969, (81 folders) (Box 12)
  - Virginia-Wyoming, 1963-1969, (54 folders) (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous states, 1963-1969, (74 folders) (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous countries, 1963-1969, (20 folders) (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous countries, 1963-1969, (11 folders) (Box 15)
- Correspondence, 1963-1969 (Box 15-18)
  Correspondence documenting the publishing of the architectural catalog.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - A-E, (20 folders) (Box 15)
  - E-G, (10 folders) (Box 16)
  - H-O, (14 folders) (Box 17)
  - P-W, (17 folders) (Box 18)
- Subject File, 1963-1969 (Box 19)
  Architectural surveys, printed matter, manuals, and reports.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Subject file, (23 folders) (Box 19)
- Architects, 1963-1969 (Box 19-24)
  Biographical material and other appropriate information on various architects compiled for the catalog.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of architect.
  - Aiken-Chandler, (34 folders) (Box 19)
  - Clark-Davis, (23 folders) (Box 20)
  - Davis-Griffin, (36 folders) (Box 21)
  - Guastavino-Plowman, (83 folders) (Box 22)
  - Poindexter-Stevens, (48 folders) (Box 23)
  - Stewardson-Zantzinger, (57 folders) (Box 24)